A predominant view in modern Buddhism is
that stream entry is a sudden
experience, primarily seen as a
combination of one's efforts and
meditation. In the way you teach, it seems to be a
In the way you teach, it seems to be a
much more gradual development, and
stream entry is more of an irreversible
and tried and tested conviction, rather
than a special experience in and of
itself. However, when looking at the simile of
However, when looking at the simile of
days to be remembered by a king, and in
contrast, the simile of the ax handle,
even the suttas seem to be divided on
that. Could both yours and the common
Could both yours and the common
interpretation be right, or are they
mutually exclusive?
Uh yeah, well, they are mutually
exclusive because um those two two
similes are not actually
at odds.
Uh it's just like
if you think that one of them is
describing a you already think the
stream entry is an experience, and then
you think one of them is describing an
experience, and the other one is
describing something else, then yeah.
But if you assume that both are
describing the same thing, and then the
Buddha was referring to really one thing
when he used the word stream entry,
rather than two,
then you would think, okay, well, these
two things have to
uh somehow be compatible.
And um
so yeah, it does say, like, for example,
um
in the same way as the king would
remember the day of his coronation, a
person would remember the day that they
attained stream entry. And it even says,
like, um somebody would remember or or
the place where somebody attained the
right view,
they would
uh like kind of honor that place or
something like that. That's a different
sutta, I think.
Um which kind of implies, like, yeah,
there is a time and place where you
would remember that you got the right
view. But you see, if you sort of go by what
But you see, if you sort of go by what
um understanding is, which is what
stream entry is.
Uh, you would see that
you would see that
there is a time when you realize that
you understood something.
Like after you've been trying
again and again for God knows how long.
You were studying, sort of trying to
wrap your head around it. Some things
made sense, other things didn't really
make sense.
It was obscured and then you sort of
tried and thought you figured it out,
but then realized it doesn't match all
this other stuff.
Uh, but then eventually there comes a
time when you realize, oh, okay, so this
is it now. I started being completely in
the dark about this and now I know what
it is.
In a in a mundane sense, obviously.
Uh, so you realize both of those are
true. You had to work in this very gradual way
You had to work in this very gradual way
to wear away that darkness that you
started with until eventually you reach
this point where you realized that you
understood, not that
something happened and then like because
of that thing that happened, you saw it.
No, the the only thing that that
happened there is you did the work and
eventually you realized that the amount
of work you did was sufficient
to reach a certain level of
understanding.
And that's that's how both of those two
things tie together. So, um, stream
entry is knowing
that you have understood the Dhamma.
Not just understanding the Dhamma.
It's a it's
Cuz see, the person who, let's say, take
a mundane example, started studying, I
don't know, calculus.
They can sort of have an experience of
understanding calculus even early on.
But are they sure that they didn't get
anything wrong? Like are they sure that
that they can now teach it to other
people and there will be no mistakes in
that in that kind of, uh,
whatever they're conveying.
So, it's knowing, being beyond doubt
that that which you have understood is
the way out of suffering.
Because you have been trying to
understand it long enough.
And then and that's also why you have
this distinction in the suttas of the
well, later became sort of
overly proliferated in the commentaries
between the path and the fruit.
That the commentary thought it was like,
oh, the the path is like the
whatever nanosecond or whatever you want
to divide it in and then the fruit is
whatever comes afterwards.
So, basically you're never actually in
the path. You just have the fruit
because it comes immediately after. But
no, in the suttas it would describe how
somebody would
uh for example, you you would be dhamma
anusari or saddha anusari, meaning
you understood the dhamma. Basically,
you have the right view. You're unable
to lose the right view.
Um but you haven't abandoned the fetters
yet. Because you're not free from doubt.
Because you're not free from doubt.
So, imagine like somebody who actually
has the right understanding of calculus.
But they're still sort of like
in that phase of like they they just
don't feel that they understood it. They
haven't realized that they got it right.
Um so uh that's what it is. It's the the
the fruit of stream entry, which is the
again the abandoning of doubt, knowing
knowing that it is that way basically,
which is what really counts as
understanding. Um
Um
is what abandons these fetters and is
what gives rise to that confidence.
So um
And you could say that's that
realization the same way as you would
remember, oh, that was the day that I
realized that I understood calculus,
having worked at it for 2 years before.
Uh in the same way, the day that I
realized that I understood the dhamma,
having worked at it for
probably even more than 2 years.
Um
So then yeah, like how could an
experience Like imagine
Like imagine
Try try to imagine that. like
you don't know anything about calculus,
but then there is an experienced
something that you will see that will that will
replace
all that work of studying and making
mistakes and just like working through
the whole thing.
You just like
How that doesn't Because that's not what
understanding is.
A picture a thing cannot give you
understanding. So,
So,
it's it's all these ideas basically just
people taking the word understanding
mystifying it into something else.
Just a vision or a or a or a
event. Um and uh yeah, that's why you have all
Um and uh yeah, that's why you have all
these views about like
And you would also have different
teachers saying completely different
things about what it is that you see
when you
get the right view, which is even more
like doesn't quite match.
Cuz yeah, then if it's a a picture that
you can or or or a
some sort of event that happens, then
yeah, it could generally be different
and you and it could be an individual
truth. Cuz he saw this, he saw this, he
saw this, and factually they all saw it,
which means I
that's right to that extent for each of
them. But an understanding
But an understanding
either matches how things are or it
doesn't. Which means there is no individual truth
Which means there is no individual truth
on that level. It's either right, which
is you see the way out of suffering and
you are actually able
to to by following that path
be completely free from it,
or you have entered a path that if you
were to follow it doesn't lead to the
ending of suffering.
So, that's why even in the in the when
the Buddha was talking about his former
teachers, um
um
he didn't say like, oh well, because you
know, they were they were
sincere practitioners and they were
really going at it. Like they sort of
discover their individual truth.
Um but I'm going to find mine now.
So, like no, as far as they went
this is not the way out of suffering and
that's wrong.
So, because yeah, it's not about like
um
sort of concede or anything. It's like
again, completely impersonally
does this cal- is this calculation
correct?
Like is this whatever formula that you
used actually going to help you
calculate the acceleration of something
or is it going to give you a number
that's just going to make you I don't
know crash and not be able to build a
proper product?
So, it either works or it doesn't
when it's understanding.
Yeah, I mean many people would
>> go after these kind of experiences then
as well to
check with somebody else
if they're actually genuine experience,
if it was a genuine experience. So, that
could show as well that it's actually
not >> Yeah. But then other people would
>> Yeah. But then other people would
describe it as a sensation, you know,
they the coolness that they experienced, the
the coolness that they experienced, the
easing of a burden that they carried
around their whole life.
Yeah, but you see all those are
experiences which again it's it's not
like somebody who is practicing
somebody who is practicing
would experience calm, would experience
a peaceful mind and so on.
But the thing is
none of that is understanding.
Those things can make you more confident
about your understanding but they could
also come from completely wrong views.
You could feel calm because you think
you're connected with God.
Does that mean it's correct just because
it
feels calm?
Um so, it's like
and that's why also you have all these
suttas talking about wrong view, uh
wrong intention, wrong speech, uh wrong
action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort,
wrong mindfulness, wrong samadhi, uh
wrong uh knowledge, wrong liberation.
uh knowledge, wrong liberation.
All the way up to liberation, it can be
wrong. If your view is wrong.
Because it's not that because you feel a
release. Like it's not that a release proves its
Like it's not that a release proves its
its a its accuracy.
You can have a wrong release.
A wrong uh burdenlessness.
Why? Because it's not you don't
understand what craving is. You don't
see it for yourself, which means
there is craving in regard to that
experience, and it's like in the dark.
Not seen as an issue. Not seen as a
thing that's binding you still to some
level of samsara.
So, that's why it's not like you can
sort of
um
take that and sort of improve on it.
It's a dead end.
Because the assumption that you're
working with there that would have
reached uh allowed you to reach those
things is that see, it's not really important
is that see, it's not really important
whether um my intentions are affected
with craving.
What's matter it what matters is that
they result in this experience.
And the whole thing was driven by that
view. And then you get there and you think,
And then you get there and you think,
"Okay, that means I'm pure." But but
the fact that that is what took you
there means
you didn't understand what craving is,
and then there is no way that you can
actually free yourself from it. There's
no way that you can free yourself from
existence. If you don't see what's binding you to
If you don't see what's binding you to
it.
So, that's why it's
it it the Buddha gave it as like a like
a like a
almost like a logical sequence of of
events. Like if you have wrong view,
for one who has wrong view, wrong
intention arises.
For one who has wrong intention, wrong
speech, and so on.
So, it's like
it's it's
it has to to
you have to actually accept
it's better not to have common
experiences.
If I'm actually
if if that means that I have to to to
reckon with this uncertainty about what
craving actually is and how I can
overcome it.
Because it's like, yeah. You can take a
medicine that removes the symptoms
immediately, not feel them anymore.
Or something that doesn't quite remove
the symptoms, but is actually addressing
the root cause and makes you feel bad
for years for as long as that root cause
hasn't been eliminated.
>> So, the
factual or the wrong liberation that
they factually experience
is not that it's not a
not a
>> liberation.
It's not that it's not liberation. Yeah,
it is a liberation of some sort.
>> Yeah.
>> Um it's not that they make it up or that
they experience something wrongly. It is
actually a factual liberation.
>> Mhm.
>> But it's just wrong.
>> Yeah, and again, it's important to see
like it's a dead end. Like because
it's a dead end. Like because
when you reach that point
and you think it's a liberation
well, it is a liberation in a way.
Um but you haven't understood what
craving is and it's sort of floating
around there.
Starting to practice would mean giving
that up.
Cuz now that's where your craving is
established. So, if you continue it
So, if you continue it
uh then yes, you haven't Let's say you
won't return to sensuality, you won't
return to these coarse things.
But the craving is being allowed to
survive just because you are still
adhering to this wrong liberation.
So, that's why it's not like, oh, it can
be sort of a stepping stone to the other
thing. It's like if you actually take on
the right practice, you would drop it.
So, that's why all those aesthetics in
in the sutras like when
let's say they were not so far off,
even then,
they completely gave up their their old
teachings, ordained under the Buddha,
and basically started from scratch.
Cuz that's the only like if you were now
starting to take the craving as your
criteria, you realize I can't do this
anymore. It's not like
I can sort of translate it.
Because it's about the craving.
And if you think that it translates
still, it's because you still think oh,
it's the experiences themselves that
have some sort of value in themselves.
As if that's what the Buddhist teaching
is about. But, no, it's about freedom
from suffering.
>> qualities that you develop through
applying your mind over years to a
meditation technique.
>> qualities, that's the are we're all
underlain by this wrong motivation. So, it's the
by this wrong motivation. So, it's the
same as like
coarse example, but let's say you kind
of um
uh quit partying and drugs and all that
stuff because you really dedicated to
your work.
And then you replace that craving with a
different one.
And that's absolutely not the same as
somebody who gave up partying by giving
up partying.
And actually, there's a sutra that talks
about that. Like he gives up killing by
giving up killing. He gives up I think
in I think it's Majjhima 54 something
like that. He gives up uh insalubrity by
giving up insalubrity, not by taking up
something else.
Cuz only then is it actually wearing
away those
tendencies that the mind has.
And then people with obviously the the
the retort to this would be well, but
didn't the Buddha say that you give up
craving by but
You Through craving, you give up
craving. Uh yes, but through craving, you give up
Uh yes, but through craving, you give up
craving.
Not through craving, I engage in another
form of craving that I hope later will
will result in me being free from
craving. It's like you are trying to give up
It's like you are trying to give up
craving now
in whatever form it takes.
And yes, you will need some amount of
craving for like some amount of
motivation to to to do that.
But you are trying to give it up. You're
not just like, "Okay, well,
fine. It kind of is there, but then it
it will go away later on its own."
So, that's why that whole path that the
Buddha taught of like suffering
Um uh sorry. Um right view and so on.
Like it's it's very common to sort of think
it's it's very common to sort of think
it's okay it sees kind of
states and practices and and um
ways of seeing things that you can sort
of just
distill and just give to anyone and they
can adopt them.
But the whole thing
the whole thing is what it is
because of that perspective that sits at
the foundation that craving is the root
of suffering. If that perspective is not
there, the whole thing collapses.
It's leading to something else.
Even if it makes you come.
>> But wouldn't that criticism
apply in the same way
to
the alternative?
Which would be like practicing the
gradual training or training oneself in
the gradual training.
That can be picked up equally
wrongly >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> as a technique, as an external
instruction that while overlooking
that while overlooking
the foundation.
>> Yeah. Well,
see, even the gradual training, like
when the sutta describe it, it's like
the person who would succeed in the
first step, they would already have the
noble aggregate of virtue.
So, in order for it to be the gradual
training like that actually leads to
Nibbana, you would already need to have
the right view.
So, really it's
it's more like you take on the precepts
so that you don't do things that make
things worse.
But, you still have to work towards that
perspective that will make that practice
right. That will sort of bind it all together
That will sort of bind it all together
and make it that you're actually giving
up greed by abstaining from these
things. Cuz you're not giving up greed unless
Cuz you're not giving up greed unless
you're seeing greed even if you're
abstaining from things rooted in greed.
Um
and and then see, yes, the same exact
and then see, yes, the same exact
practice externally could coexist
with those very different points of
view. Like one person could be
Like one person could be
uh
keeping the precepts with that
perspective that well, any craving is
the root of suffering. Any craving is is
the reason why
it's my enemy, basically. It's the
reason why I'm practicing.
Um
and then they would see, well,
I'm abstaining from breaking the
precepts because that's rooted in
craving. But, then they would see all these uh
But, then they would see all these uh
impulses that would usually arise when
people start keeping the precepts
without the right view to like sort of
um
intensify. Add more observances, add more rules,
Add more observances, add more rules,
add more things that will make you feel
safer. A person who's operating with the right
A person who's operating with the right
perspective would see, wait, this is
wrong. I shouldn't give in to this.
I shouldn't give in to this.
I shouldn't give in to breaking the
precepts either
because both are rooted in craving.
And that's how you arrive at the middle
way, which is you don't do either of them.
which is you don't do either of them.
Because
see, the lust is unwholesome. The
restlessness, the doubt
is unwholesome.
But, if you're not operating from that
perspective and you just
have this kind of abstract idea of
renunciation that like, "Okay, it's
giving things up."
Whatever internal state that involves.
Uh then sure, you're giving the lust,
but what about the other half?
So then it's not the middle way anymore.
And it's not going to lead you to the
extinction of suffering cuz that fire
it's just being given different fuel
now. It's not even gone.
So yeah, then
right view
would transform even though nothing
would change externally in your in your
adherence to the precepts.
But it would transform the whole thing.
Like you would be free from silabbata
paramasa.
You would be free from the self view
that also is
inherently tied with that virtue as
well. Like me as the sort of
um
a certain identity, let's say, of a
beholding those observances
well enough and stuff.
Which you would hear that and it would
sound like, "Okay, so then you sort of
don't identify it with it, which means
you sometimes break it."
Well, no. That's because it's the middle
way. It's neither of them.
>> So that's why the emphasis in the
beginning is more about the
abstaining from certain things
rather than believing things which are
informed by the wrong view by the wrong
perspective. >> would bring you closer, yeah. If if you
>> would bring you closer, yeah. If if you
kind of recognize it's not about
anything that you do as in like, "Okay,
I Let's say I'm I'm celibate."
But then I also make a practice of every
single day
just reminding myself like
of why I should be celibate.
And it's like, see that That's not that
that practice is bad. The Buddha might
even have talked about it.
But the thing is you are doing it in a
way that excuses
this clear unwholesome state. It it
basically justifies itself regardless of
whether there is any lust or not, which
are they meant which there may not be. So then
So then
that's what the Buddha meant like you
you give things up without taking up
give things up without taking up
something else. That's what the wise man
does.
But the fool takes up one thing to
replace the other one.
>> So if I'm the person who judges
that I know
what the practice is, that I have the
right view.
How do I make sure
that I really know
>> Mhm.
>> and not delude myself into knowing?
>> Yeah, well the
I probably the first thing is to ask
yourself like
uh why do you want to be sure that you
know?
Cuz see if you're trying to find a
certainty that's very different from
that's very different from
actually being unable to doubt.
Cuz inability to doubt does not depend
on you deciding
that you do have the right view.
So um
it's like if you're able to leave it
ambiguous and not have to to come to an answer to
and not have to to come to an answer to
it
then and not be bothered by that
and you are also aware that you have
abandoned all these things then let's
say that's that's closer. But at the end
of the day
uh well yeah, you can always delude
yourself. Like all these uh I've been
mentioning a couple times now, all these
uh
um
teachers of the Buddha had before
they genuinely thought and they they
even described themselves as Tathagatas
sometimes, I think.
Like the one who is
who's gone basically.
Um and uh the how how could let See, not
even then. There was not even an
external criteria
that could have saved them because the
Dharma was just not there.
Uh so
but fortunately, see,
uh you do have an external criteria that
you can apply internally
that you can see to be true internally.
Uh and that's what we said before in the
previous talk, which is like
do I still suffer?
So, cuz see
it's easy to sort of um
it's it's inevitable almost to to sort
of
descend into these the the more of the
emphasis on what you understood and and
how far you came and
basically focusing on all the positive
things. Not seeing
Not seeing
the massive
garbage that might still be there of
things that
are still clearly evidence of you not
seeing the way out.
Um so, for example
uh
being challenged.
That's a common one.
Like when people would would
think that they have the right view, but
then somebody challenges that
somebody challenges that
and they automatically feel like a need
to defend it.
Um when
uh
the is cuz see, yeah.
Um
uh so, the path is certainly not free
from uh
uh
sensual desire, ill will, and all these
things. But there's a crucial difference between
But there's a crucial difference between
that and what people think their so the
path is usually think, which is
um it's not a problem
because a layperson, for example
uh
so, you would see all these these kind
of threads of like so
if somebody actually sees for themselves
that craving is the root of suffering
and they're beyond doubt, about this,
doubt, would they be able to see the most
would they be able to see the most
obvious form of craving in their lives
and still not think that they have to
give it up?
Now, that's independent of whether they
actually do give it up,
as in they have enough diligence to go
against their own desire, but the fact
that they try to justify it or or try to
like not feel like it's an issue,
not feel like it's an issue,
for example,
uh that already cast serious doubt on
that understanding cuz means you're not
beyond doubt that craving is the root of
suffering. Um Um
and um
so yeah, you you you kind of
let's say if you want to doubt it,
and you want to to prove that it's
wrong, you will be able to cuz there are
all these kind of
different angles
that that uh well, even the Buddha gave
in the suttas.
And if you're really honest about like
you you want to
to prove yourself wrong, basically, cuz
you you're rightly scared of that trap
of thinking that you know what you
don't, which the Buddha said is like
destroys you, basically.
Then uh you will be coming at it from the
uh you will be coming at it from the
opposite perspective rather than
trying to find how many suttas I can see
to to to um
validate my experience of sotapatti.
my experience of sotapatti.
Uh you will be looking at it like, "No,
I I don't want to
I want to find evidence against this,
basically, cuz if I can find evidence of
more work to do,
that's only going to be in my benefit."
Uh so, and that's why like at the end of
the day, it's not even
uh necessary.
It's not that it gives you
something special
uh to know that you're a sotapanna. Like
the Buddha didn't talk about those uh
distinctions in the beginning.
He revealed that later towards the end
of his life, in fact, when um
people were asking him about the
rebirths of some of his disciples.
Um so, it's like
it in a way it's better to just keep up
that clarity of do I know that I'm
liable to suffering still?
And then, it doesn't matter as as the
Buddha himself said, it doesn't matter
if it's a little or a lot.
In the same way as excrement, all of it
smells equally bad.
You see, it all comes down to that sense
of
urgency that like that has to be
triggered by, as I said before,
seeing the real living
um
sufferings that you're still subject to.
The real shortcomings that you still
have. Not minimizing them. Not saying like,
Not minimizing them. Not saying like,
"Oh, well, see,
uh I I had this great experience and
then sort of automatically you focus on
that." You you immediately
You you immediately
uh you can't at the same time recognize
all the stuff that you're still liable
to, all the stuff that you haven't
developed. So, keep that as a as a as a
as a rule of thumb, like always focus on
uh the shortcomings,
on the on the things that you haven't
developed, on the things that still
pressure you, on the things that still
trigger you.
And that's what the Buddha himself said.
He said he he he There were two things
that that he came to know in the process
of becoming a Buddha,
and it was non-contentment with actual
wholesome states, like things that he
knew were wholesome, not even like, "Oh,
I feel this had this experience and it
feels good, therefore it must be
wholesome." No, the actual wholesome
things. And then,
And then,
um uh relentless striving.
So, like there is no benefit at all,
no matter how far you went,
to be to be content with to be
complacent. And to start kind of
And to start kind of
slowly
uh devaluing and deemphasizing
all the the drawbacks and all the
um imperfections that your current state
of being still has. >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> So, in the end it boils down to
not really being concerned about or
defensive if one has the right view or not, but
if one has the right view or not, but
keep applying the question of am I still
suffering and trying to uncover
whatever is still there.
Uh yes, but at the same time um
you have to keep in mind
you have to question your own views
about what suffering is.
You can't just say, "Oh, am I allowed
suffering?" And then take for granted
that what that question is going to point to
what that question is going to point to
in yourself
is accurate. And And it's like, "Oh, I
have 50% left, and that's That's good."
No. It's like that very place that you're
It's like that very place that you're
looking to find the suffering might not
be the right one.
But you see
that's one thing.
The other thing is like
if you're subject to craving, you will
be suffering anyway.
So, it's like
you can know that you suffer.
That's for sure.
You may not be able to pinpoint what the
suffering is, why that suffering is
there. Uh how to put an end to it.
Uh how to put an end to it.
But if you should you sort of leave it
on that ambiguous level, don't don't
overly kind of insert the explanations into it,
kind of insert the explanations into it,
you can see, "Yes, I still suffer."
So, you keep that as the background.
And you see, "Okay, I have to tweak and
and upgrade and seriously question even
my views about what suffering is."
Knowing that on that vague level I still
suffer, but I just don't understand even
that enough.
But I know that it's there.
So, that's how you would be kind of
progressing in the right way. It's like
you know that there's a problem.
Well, in the same way as as like the
example of
studying any subject. Like you know that
you don't understand it.
But you also know that you don't know
how much you don't understand it. So,
it's just this kind of vague impression
that I don't know.
And you are willing to question
basically every assumption you have
about that subject, which is how you
become an expert at anything.
But if if you if you could kind of don't
catch yourself drifting
into that sort of taking for granted of
little assumptions that you started with.
assumptions that you started with.
Uh then you would carry that like
with you
indefinitely. And see, it's not like
with some, I don't know, carpentry or
some, I don't know, carpentry or
something with like you can meet a
professional carpenter and he can
visually show you that you're doing
something wrong.
Here, nobody can tell you because
you might again you might even become
so it's like
wrongly. So, it's not even like there
would be these super coarse signs of
that you're doing something wrong.
So, you would have to
have that as I said that that drive
to find the drawbacks, to find the
imperfections, and actually
actually feel a sense of fear.
Like that's what the sense of urgency
is. San Vega. And in fact, the the
the word for fear and the sense of
urgency is sometimes the same.
Is used the same way.
So, it has to be like existentially
touching you. That recognition of I
don't know.
Rather than like
okay, I don't know, but like it's fine.